welcome to launched I'm Charlie Chapman
and today I'm excited to bring you the
developer behind the popular iOS
emulator app Delta and the thirdparty
App Store alt store Riley test
[Music]
it Riley welcome to the show hey Charlie
nice to be here thanks for having me on
I am I think we talked about you coming
on like what two years ago or something
like that yeah a while back who knows
just
yeah it's we've we've met a couple times
uh I think I think every time has been
in California wwc exactly um but yeah
for anybody you know listening at home
this is this is the first recording the
first episode real episode I've done of
this in over a year other than like the
special episodes the live episodes that
I did last year so uh so yeah we're
we're going to be rusty uh but uh
luckily we have a really interesting
unique story here to tell so uh I think
I think that will make it easy to get
through uh but thank you thank you for
coming on I I'm excited to talk about
the like Whirlwind experience you've had
over the last I guess year and a half I
mean it's a longer Journey but really
the last year and a half kind yeah
perfect word just insane just so hectic
but and all the best ways like can't
really complain just a wild ride yeah
and I was telling you right before we
started recording but uh you you you
decided to make this an even more
dramatic start for me because the day
before we started recording uh suddenly
you're in the news you're giving like
press
releases uh for some dramatic goings on
with your with your alt store uh which
we'll get into just another Tuesday you
know Apple saying stuff about
us never never a dull moment in uh in
alt store Land um but before we get into
alt store and Delta and hot tub and all
of the the craziness of the last year uh
I want to give everyone you know an idea
of who you are uh so the three questions
I always ask everybody to kick off the
show is where are you from do you have a
formal education related to what you do
and then let's just talk about the
journey that sort of LED ultimately up
to Delta and all of this craziness sure
okay then yeah I'll start with that
where I'm from I was born in Dallas
Texas and I lived there for a few years
but then when I was five my family moved
to New Zealand and so I actually grew up
like in New Zealand and that's to me
where I think of like my foundational
childhood and where I learned so much of
who I am or got much of who I am today
and New Zealand's great everyone should
check it out I love it there but then oh
it's it's on my like very high list of
places it's such an incredible place and
I want to visit so much of Like My
Philosophy I think on work and
everything is from that culture like
they're very great people lovely people
but whatever that's a Sidetrack so yeah
grew up in New Zealand moved back to
America and then I was in Texas all
throughout high school and then went to
California for like college at
University of Southern California and
that's where I studied computer science
and so I did study computer science I
graduated with a just a CS degree a
bachelor's nothing too fancy and through
that time you were you were building
apps like in high school and in college
right yes so I started building apps
when I was I think in seventh grade
because I like adjust my sister got the
iPhone and I was obsessed with that I
was like what is this device it's so
cool and so then I like saved up all my
money to buy the iPhone 3G and then I
just fell in love with all the apps like
the App Store had just come out and so I
had to download like so many apps like I
remember like tap oh man so many apps
tapt Revenge what the twinkle the like
pre the twific aim all that stuff and so
just playing around with that gave me
like so much just inspired me to make my
own and so yeah I then bought my myself
like a programming book this is before
there were like tutorials online and
like taught myself some did you already
have a Mac then
I begged my parents to get me a Mac
because they were trying to give us a
laptops for school and I had to hand me
down Windows computer and I was like
please I really want to make apps even
though I had no experience and so it my
parents were like honestly I'm thank God
they were willing to trust or like to
believe in me I like sure we'll get to a
Mac instead of a PC and see what we can
do with it so I did that this is like
this is a weird aside but this is
something that's been on my mind
recently because I have kids that are
like they're they're young enough that
they're not quite in that phase of like
you know they're going to do the thing
that they do for the rest of their life
or whatever but like I hear you know
your story right there or uh like when I
was watching uh uh Steven Spielberg's uh
the fabl men's movie and I've obviously
read about his history too and he talks
about how like it was like his uncle or
something I think JJ Abrams has a
similar story where it's like some body
in their life spoiled them with some
piece of gear yeah that when you're in
that certain part of your life where you
get like super obsessed with something
if you're the right kid that gets handed
the right thing that clicks with your
brain you get like such a crazy
Advantage uh yes absolutely because it's
even even right after college like you
might not be married you might not have
kids but you still are now running a
life sort of but during that phase of
high school your life is in such a weird
way and your brain is forming in such a
weird way that like it's crazy how deep
into the crevices of understanding
something you can get even though you're
obviously ignorant about the rest of the
world uh and it gives you such a leg up
later on that really is exactly what it
was like it was the perfect timing I
obsessed over programming I had no
programming experience but then I
learned Objective C fell in love with it
and like just it was my obsession I
followed all the iPhone like Tech blogs
the programming blogs exactly cuz it was
just that that ripe age for me to be so
obsessed with programing and apple as
well so very yes that's very formational
for me getting the Mac that's so cool so
you were building apps did you release
any of those like into the store like
are you one of those like early on you
know millionaire kids releasing a f app
or something no not at all I my first
app was extremely basic it was called
shoot around and it was literally just
like a camera Fe the camera feed and I
had like lasers and but like you had
buttons you would just press and it
would shoot lasers at the camera feed
but it was all designed in Microsoft
Paint like the buttons were just like
blue circles the lasers were lit
Microsoft Paint so you use the you use
the PC to create your assets exactly cuz
I exactly I didn't know how to use any
gra any designer tools on the Mac yet
but I new paint that is interesting I've
never thought of that I guess cuz Mac
paint was sort of famously with like the
original Mac and stuff but like there's
not really a version of
that exactly like for people who know
nothing which me at the time I was like
yeah I I had to pull out my old Windows
PC to make use paint and so I mean I
would have recommended the app icon also
made in paint it is not a good app icon
at all like it's very bad but at the
time I was like you need to send me that
app icon and I should make it the
chapter art for this sketch version of
that app icon yeah I was proud of at the
time I was like oh it looks like a
camera look and does not at all but but
like that was my first I think learning
of like there's more to make making an
app than just the code cuz I was like
you know here's the app and then I was
like I got to like make an icon for it I
got to like make a website or I got to
talk about it and it was just like
whatever I learned there's so much more
that went into like this project but i'
digress yeah ah no and that's that
that's the stuff that's so cool again
especially as a kid
getting you know it's like doing
projects in school is super helpful for
understanding how to fill out forms and
do all this stuff but it's not self
motivated but when it's something
selfmotivated it's like a completely
different thing and it absolutely it
sets you up you know uh going forward so
much oh yeah so okay so you You released
some of them in the store were did you
ever like did you make any sales were
they all free like what was the story
there I did yeah so I end up then my
next app I made was camera Prime and
that actually was did decently well at
the time it was a camera app with like
extra features that the normal camera
app didn't have at the time like Zoom or
Burst Mode like very basic features that
just weren't there at all and so that
was my start and that actually did kind
of well I made like several hundred
dollars a month just passively in high
school and so which is amazing it was
for high school it was incredible I was
like oh wow I can just put this and just
get money every month and then use it on
whatever so that was also like really
motivating just to know that it was
possible like that was the first time I
had any app that like got reviews people
reviewed it said it was cool and so I
don't know it yeah just that confirm
that human beings somewhere else in the
world especially when it's like not the
us although I guess you were already a
world traveler at that point but uh the
idea of somebody else out in the world
like seeing a thing you made and and
having some experience with it is so
magical oh it really was yeah I remember
posting about it like on the Mac Rumors
forums like trying to promote it and
people were just like wow what a cool
app and I was like oh like just I don't
know such great validation Ah that's so
cool so this is in high school now this
is around the time when GBA for IOS
happened right so what's the story there
because that's sort of the the beginning
of your Arc so to speak leading to now I
guess and yeah it started just like as a
basically an accident so I was fully
focused on camera Prime that's what I
thought was going to be like my main app
was what I was going to be known for and
then I just came across like some an
open source repo for a jailbreak Game
Boy Band simulator called GPS gpsp or no
GPS phone and so I just found that and I
was like wait this is just the code
could I download this code and run it
locally like for myself without
jailbreaking because I've never been a
Jailbreaker I don't like it it's not
something I just want to do with my
phone I actually like my phone being
like pristine and apple
like people that know you now for alt
store and Delta we'll probably be and
don't know you personally we'll probably
be surprised to hear that I know it's I
know it's funny to me because also
people always say oh Delta was like
around on the jailbreak phones forever
and I was like it was never available
for jailbroken phones because I the
whole point was that I didn't want a
jailbreak so I was Finding ways to not
jailbreak and get out there and your
reason for that and let me paraphrase
and then you correct me but based on
what we've talked about and what you've
talked about before is that you
genuinely do value the like protection
layers that Apple puts on iOS you're not
like iOS should be like Android and just
be completely blown wide open like you
genuinely buy into a lot of the
arguments for why iOS is so lock down
it's obviously you think not to the same
degree that it is exactly like 99% I
agree with like the status quo I think
it is well I really do agree with the
status quo for pretty much everyone I
don't want that to change I just think
yeah I love the iOS platform I love how
streamlined it is like I don't like
using my Mac I actively dislike using
anything that's not like an iOS device
because it feels like work to me versus
like using a phone even I'm using
productive tasks doesn't feel that way
and that's so I love it for those kind
of reasons and so no I would never want
iPhone to become Android at all cuz I
exact for the same reasons I just don't
want that experience that's not
appealing to me I want the very polished
lock down
experience yeah that's that's crazy so
GBA for I well this is before that
existed so you you saw that there was a
jailbreak emulator that and so I was
like okay this is cool I downloaded it
and I just like it didn't compile at all
but I was so determined I was like I
want this on my phone so I spent
literally like I think at the time like
3 months like hacking away at learning
how to like cuz I was so new to like
this whole thing I to learn and how to
fix all these compiler erors and then I
finally got it compiling and then I got
out my phone and I remember like I
loaded up Pokemon emerald and that was
like just one of those magical moments
in like my career just like wait Pokemon
is running on my phone like for real
like I didn't jailbreak it's just
happening and I thought it was the
coolest thing in the world and so that's
was like you know what I'm going to make
this you know at least available for
people like as again it just was in the
App Store I didn't think it'd be
anything so I just decided to polish it
up a bit make it like a real App instead
of like this hack together thing and I
put it basically up on GitHub again open
source and called it GB and the original
one the original one was also for iOS uh
yes it was yes okay it just didn't work
it just was for jailbroken phones so oh
right right right only for jailbroken
phones so you've you basically built it
in a way where you could you could pull
down the source code if you had at the
time did you have to have your own
developer account or was that after they
had opened okay so you had to have a
developer account uh but if you had a
developer account you could pull the
code down and then you could sideload it
on your phone through xcode exactly yeah
and that's what I thought was going to
that's what I thought was going to be
the end of it and then what really just
like changed was when there is this
service came out Mac build server and
they just allowed you to hook up any
GitHub project open source GitHub iOS
project to their service which resigned
apps with an Enterprise certificate so
you could basically connect this and
then resign with entprise certificate
and then anyone could download your app
from GitHub if it was open source
without having to
jailbreak okay so and like if you're not
aware the Enterprise certificate program
the reason for that is if you're a
company that builds an app internally
such as for example Apple uh cuz they
have like apps that only employees can
use and stuff you can like if you get
the special certificate from Apple you
can build kind of your own little store
uh on the web where people that are
internal to your company can download
and run an app that really is only for
employees it's like a really like
specific lockdown program that Apple set
up for companies so you have to get one
of these certificates which is a whole
process to get uh and so this company
you said it was Mac Mac which one was it
build server Mac build server they set
up some kind of system they get a hold
of one of these I guess and set up a
system where you could have their build
server do the thing where it downloads
from uh GitHub repo builds it resigns it
with their certificate and then they
host it as well they hosted it and so
you could in a way that you could just
directly download it from your phone
like from Safari and that oh that's
interesting I I missed this whole like
era no it was very interesting cuz this
is before you had the free developer
account so it was there were very like
little ways to install an app outside
the app store without paying apple and
so this was was was it was the developer
account $100 then or was that back when
it was still really expensive too um I I
think for Enterprise it's a little more
expensive to get Enterprise certificate
I'm not sure well for Enterprise I just
meant for the idea of side loading your
own stuff it would still be $100 like it
was $100 yeah but that's still that's a
huge especially for the market of people
who want UL ERS yep exactly significant
portion of them $100 is probably outside
of their budget exactly so this was I
didn't expect it to be a big deal but it
turned out that just having the ability
to download an emulator from Safari on
your phone was a big deal and basically
that was then that just blew up and then
people started posting about it and like
making Reddit posts and then I was like
oh my God I I didn't realize there was
actually this much demand for this kind
of thing and it caught me off guard and
so that's when I decided to take it
seriously and I made GBA FRS like my
real Endeavor because you know what this
is a real app I'm going to now like
spend my whole basically senior year of
high school working on it making a new
version that can be released and I like
brought my best friend Paul Thorson on
board like to help me design the whole
thing and we were like okay let's do
this we're going to release this
officially using this Enterprise
certificate method and just see what
happens you sell it or was it did it was
it just totally free it was just free we
were just like wanting to get out there
we thought it was so cool like and also
we're in high school so we're like I
would really care about the money part
but yeah so so starts the mythology of
Riley is just so desperate for people to
be able to play Pokemon on their iPhones
it seems exactly it's like your driving
force as a of as a human it almost seems
like uh that is I mean that is what it
has felt like like I just want to get
this out there and I do believe that
like it's so much better having it free
out there and having all these people
discover this amazing thing versus
having charging anything for it like I
don't know I get more value of seeing
just like people love it so much and it
probably wasn't necessarily
strategically on your mind as a high
schooler but uh
avoiding it's it's an area ripe for uh
legal like scare emails and so if you're
not making a bunch of money for it that
probably helps in that regard quite a
bit too exactly so that really did help
it just was safe and then yeah so we
released that and then was really big
really popular got millions of downloads
and then it no it was pretty wild and
then the weird part was cuz Apple shut
down the entprise certificate pretty
quickly but then there was a bug in iOS
where if you just set your date back by
24 hours it then the Enterprise
certificate check didn't work so you
could just set your date back by day and
then go to website and download GBA for
IOS and it would work and it was very it
was just a bug very weird yeah but that
was like how people downloaded basically
GBA for the entire lifetime was that
method it was called the date trick very
that's crazy so for so it lived on for
quite a while even after they yeah
revoked that c they released an update I
update on my birthday that broke it oh
no that was fun it like got oh and it
fixed the bug I was relying on I was
like oh happy birthday to me oh man okay
so at that point uh Not only was it
nobody could download it but it was also
like then it was it didn't even work on
people's phones right so it's it's now
dead mhm you still in high school or had
you were you in college by this point I
just graduated high school and I was
taking a semester off between high
school and college at this point okay so
I was basically about to go into college
and so to me I was like you know what
fine the end of this experience let's
move on to something else let's move on
something normal a normal app store app
maybe right and then you just joined a
large company and you spent the rest of
your days uhing yeah tickets right yeah
doing nothing interesting y for sure so
okay so how do we get from this moment
where everything seems pretty normal to
uh I guess Delta would be sort of the
next the next stage yeah and then it
wasn't even that long but the I was not
planning to work build another emulator
but Apple announced Swift like that
summer and then so I was at college and
I like between my classes I was like I
kind of wanted like a project to work on
and so I was like you know I kind of
want to learn Swift I really should be
learning Swift like I'm an iOS Developer
it's something I should do and so I was
like like yeah what's a project I should
work on and then I was like ah you know
I'll make a fun little emulator for me
like just like a toy thing to like just
test my skills like to test like project
architecture like just a personal
project like all those kind of things
and learn swi was it just
rebuilding like on your own the GBA for
IOS app then or was there something
different that you were going for it was
rewriting the app to be more like
sensible better General but not the core
itself like I wasn't trying to write
like the emulation engine myself but the
GBA firest app was like thrown together
for in high school and I wanted now like
to teach myself better architecture
design like I wanted all of the cores
like in their own Frameworks and I want
like my own framework that called
through like I just wanted that type of
thing and so this felt like a cool way
to build it out and so that's what
started with Delta and it was just going
to be my personal app until I went to
WWDC that year and I talked to app
review and I was like hey is there any
chance I could get this app approved and
then they were like yeah we we don't see
a reason we couldn't approve it we just
worry about like the open pipeline for
games but if you just you know submitted
it to us and gave us a white list of
games to approve that should work and
this was at WWDC like you had a ticket
you were in the labs and so you could
actually talk to people on the app
review team exactly yeah and so it it
was like like oh cool very I that took
that as a great sign that I could get
this in the App Store so I was like
awesome I'm now going to commit like so
much of my time to making Delta an
official app so it could be in the App
Store and yeah this is back in 2015 and
I was like wow this is amazing I'm so
excited and so then yeah I spent like
the next year working on it like again
while in college but like spending so
much time on it and then I went back to
WBC the next year talked to them and
they were like actually no no no no no
no like was it the same people I did
talk to the same person and he was like
oh no I talk to the higher ups we don't
allow emulators and I was like and you
know it's nice to hear that officially
because that was never an official rule
at least it wasn't after you had
submitted I guess but I me I was still I
was pretty pissed I was like yeah yeah I
had spent my whole past year like
building this thing cuz you said I could
I wouldn't have wasted that much time
building it and so I was pretty pissed
off at the time and I was just like what
am I supposed to do now but it was just
like a also at that time Apple announced
the whole free developer account or that
you could install apps for free with
xcode with an Apple ID without having to
pay yeah there's essentially a free mode
to a developer account now where yeah
you can like build your own apps there's
limits like you can only run those apps
for 3 days after you push it meod you
get seven days but you only get three at
a time you can only have three at a time
installed and you can only register 10
app IDs in a week there's so many weird
restrictions there's a bunch of
limitations to stop somebody if anybody
were to ever try to make yeah crazy some
mechanism where you could like uh make
it easy for people to Sid load yeah but
no so exactly there were so many
restrictions in place because Apple
literally just did not want this to
exist but I was desperate I was like I
have Delta it's like close to completion
and and I just saw that Apple announced
this and I just knew that there was some
way to like use that to get dealt out
there was basically just what I knew and
so then I spent the next like few years
working on what that was and like
researching I had to learned so much
about like code signing I had to learned
how the whole process worked and but it
was all just because like I already had
Delta ready to go and or close to ready
to go and I just needed to get out there
somehow and I refused to just give up on
it because I was like this deserves to
be in the world everyone people want it
so yeah so I worked on that for several
years and that's what became the first
version of alt store when I finally
launched okay so this is while this is
all while you're in college then still
um all while college and then continued
while after I graduated I was after I
graduated I went to working fulltime on
building alt store while also like doing
contract work to fund that gotcha so
this is like this is what you want to do
in your head was Delta and ALT store and
somehow build this into some kind of
system system that ultimately lets you
release Delta exactly we haven't
actually talked much about Delta at this
point but
like uh it was basically a nice iOS
Feeling
app emulator right yeah was it what were
the what were the main like the original
um uh platforms that you supported or
like consoles that you supported I mean
pretty much all the ones today except
for Nintendo DS so it was Nintendo the
NES
SNES uh n6 4 and then Game Boy Color and
Game Boy Advance I think yeah okay those
five and you could in the emulators
themselves there's all sorts of
different projects out in the world so
it was I mean I'm sure it was work but
it was relatively easy to like pull
those in and run those on yeah I would
yeah relatively easy compared to I mean
yes compared to building the app pulling
them in was not the hardest part because
I didn't have to build like if I had to
build the am core yes absolutely it
would have been the hardest part but yes
it was kind of like a fun challenge of
like how do I take this code base and
then incorporate it into like the
framework that I was building what I
call Delta cor and so it was like a fun
yeah just challenge for me doing all
that and the emulator itself then is
essentially running in a in a box uh in
your app and then the the frame and the
buttons that exactly and the design of
the the emulator like UI that's where
your Delta the app that you're writing
is coming into play yeah and so I'll say
my wanting to have a good architecture
for this has paid off very well like it
is actually it's pretty easy for me to
take a just a new emulator core and wrap
it up in the Delta core framework that
I've made and then everything just works
because it's basically I need to find
what's the input mechanism how do I get
a video buffer out how do I get the
audio buffer out and once I just connect
all those pieces then like you said it
just runs into the box and outputs to
Delta core which does all the other
stuff I imagine that makes the the
different like designs that you have
work as well like colors or something
like that right yes exactly that's cool
okay so uh Apple releases a new
mechanism to make it free for people to
run apps in some capacity from meod to
their phone you uh in your maniacal goal
to make Pokemon available for people on
crazy world Domin I'm going to do this
we're going to come up with a way and so
you spent years literally just trying to
figure out a mechanism that
is what I'm gathering based on the end
result your goal was to make it a as
seamless as you could experience for
people exactly to be able to to download
this so what did all that kind of lead
up to ultimately then uh first like
version of this oh the first version uh
was a glorified Delta installer like so
when you first launched like I launched
it back in 2019 like September 2019 that
was the launch of alt store and I said
everything about it how it's the
storefront but it literally could only
install Delta it was just a Delta
installer basically because I just
wanted to like make sure this whole
thing worked before I opened up this
whole platform or something and so I
launched that it could just install
Delta and I and what what is that is it
a website is it a so it is itself a
native app and so how that works was I
had a desktop app you downloaded on your
computer for Mac or P for Mac yeah Mac
or PC called alt server and then you use
that program to you give you give that
program your Apple ID and password and
then it signs them with apple configures
your account and then resigns the alster
app and installs it onto your phone and
then it's as if you were the developer
that installed it yourself in Mex code
and so it's incredibly Jank no it's so
it's so many pieces but the important
thing was how can I put together in a
good enough like flow like it just had
to be a basic and now we ask people for
their literal Apple ID and passwords
that was the biggest deterrent by far
and I was it was funny to see that a lot
of people didn't care like people just
did just put it and I was like oh man I
mean like we tell people give it like
make a fake account use a throwaway
account we don't care like we literally
don't care what you give us we just need
a valid Apple ID that we can configure
most people because Apple doesn't have
apis for you to do this yes like to ask
for a token for example uh correct yeah
for some sort of Factor off or something
system cuz this isn't a mechanism that
they
necessarily wanted to support this did
predate I think the App Store connect
API but even now you can't do what alt
store does with the official API because
yeah exactly yeah like there's apps out
there uh other iOS developers might be
aware of a bunch of different apps out
there that let you um do a lot of App
Store connect things inside of an app um
and those use the app store connect API
but I'm I mean I'm not speaking on
behalf of anybody I just I'm fairly
certain that most of those are still
doing quite a bit of like web scraping
and stuff to to do some of the more
advanced things because it's just
there's not apis for that yep and same
thing so yeah we were using the API that
xod was using at the time basically just
to generate the free developer count and
everything so not official that makes
sense that's crazy though I you I didn't
know there was a there was a PC version
of this as well oh yeah so what did you
build this Mac and PC app with oh I had
the original plan was to use which is
stupid I wanted to use Objective C and
use the window Microsoft's like win
Objective C framework to Port that yeah
and so I wrote like all of the code
signing and like apple code and
Objective C to plan like to reuse it and
then I could not get it to work at all
and I was just like oh my God I I'm just
going to have to write this from scratch
all over again for Windows and so I did
I literally took like like I think a
week and it was awful and I just rewrote
my entire code base for alt server on
the Mac in C++ for windows with also I
no experience before this I was like I
got to learn this all I knew was a C++
learnu it there there is it's a menu bar
app so oh okay that's fair which is also
how I got away with able to do it on the
map too it just a menu bar app you
tapped and then you said install alt
store and it would install alt store so
man imagine like how much easier e that
would be Now with uh I know with all
these like AI tools to be like hey give
me that same thing but in this language
there's so many way like today would be
so much EAS also cuz Swift has now works
natively on Windows that was like what
killed me I there's also a whole bunch
of crossplatform Frameworks that I B on
Objective C being the cross plat which
was so stupid and hindsight I was like
oh so now I still the only objective c
an ALT store was my core framework that
I intended to port to Windows that never
did so I'm like whatever unfortunate
that's funny
yeah okay so so you went through all of
this you built a surprisingly smooth
experience to essentially release Delta
or to make Delta available but you
called it alt store yes um what leading
into that like the launch itself that
you did for alt store
Delta um were you were you sort of
marketing it as this is a new
alternative store or were you really
marketing the emulator Delta I was yeah
marketing as the store because I wanted
to do more without store and to me so
much of the motivation for doing this
was that if I'm going to do all this
effort to get Delta out there I might as
well do it in a way that other
developers can take advantage of it as
well yeah and so that was like that was
so motivating for me because I don't
like I don't know if I would have done
all this truly just for Delta but just
knowing that this could allow other
types of apps I don't know that was cool
so then that was motivation behind that
and then and then what was the reaction
to both the the emulator and the alt
store I mean emulator was great cuz
there there was like this core community
of people who had been following me
since the GBA days and so they were
stoked to have that out they loved it
that there's an official way to finally
install it I will never forget though
like the reaction to alt store like all
the comments were like this is stupid
Apple's going to shut this down
immediately why would anyone waste their
time on it and I was like just like roll
my eyes like oh my God I like I can't
believe this is the reaction from
everyone and so but whatever so that was
but it was still excited like it made a
lot of rounds so people liked it they
thought there's no way it's going to
stick around Apple's going to shut it
down immediately yeah and then to their
credit the next month Apple did shut
down the private apis we were using to
sign in to App Store connect and make
all these so that was a very stressful
time and I had to figure out Apple's new
authentication mechanism
and write that in alt store and it was
completely broken so for about a couple
do you think they changed it for that
reason 100% it was 100% well I didn't
know if it was one of those where it's
like they made changes and it broke you
or if it was like they made changes to
make it harder for you it was we were
using something like by the time altar
launched xcode was no longer using this
thing anymore so it was like a I mean is
just happing but it was two weeks
afterwards and then it just like shut
down and away and I was like uh-huh and
again I mean whatever good for them good
move like whatever so we this is I
wanted to talk about this actually even
just what you just said there this has
been a thing through I mean we'll get to
you know you parading through the EU and
talking to Parliament and whatever uh
you have maintained that exact attitude
frequently and I've been so impressed by
it I think I told you this in person
last year too but
like I feel like most people who do the
type of thing you're doing where you're
pushing bound
MH uh and trying to open things up
there's this
uh like what's antagonizing attitude
where it's like any opportunity to cry
foul it's like anger look they're
they're they're the big man's pushing us
down or whatever Y and I kind of I'm not
that personality type I find it kind of
grading but I also appreciate that you
need that's how change happens or
whatever right like I kind of had that
attitude but you have managed somehow
through all of this to keep
a very understanding attitude like you
will you are not shy to be like mad or
angry about things that I don't want to
say like you're passive yeah but like
when you frequently you'll say that like
fair enough and you'll explain exactly
why they would do what they do what is
that just something about your
personality that you've always had is
that something you've had to work on
were you like that in the early days or
uh well first thank you for saying that
I appreciate that cuz yeah something I
do try really hard with and I don't know
I'm kind of like you it's like I don't
like that approach in general like I it
turns me off a little bit but I I don't
know to me this is like like a lot of my
like New Zealand upbringing I don't know
like it's like this is kind of like the
cultural there it's like I don't know
like chill out like things are just not
that big a deal and it just so just a
mix of things I just I also just respect
Apple so much I love them so much and I
don't I don't hate Apple I really don't
and I know this is just such a complex
issue I and I just also know that
there's so many strong opinions on both
sides and so yes it's just very
complicated but yeah I do it because
it's I think it is just the best way to
honestly make change I don't think just
yelling about stuff is the way that the
biggest change will be made we've very
much tried to work with apple like
especially in the beginning after we
launched like altstore pal we were
very much trying to work with them and
hopefully trying to align with them they
did not return the favor they did not
work with us and so we had to change our
tactics but so exactly it's kind of like
I'll give them benefit of doubt I do
think they are trying here but I'm yeah
I'm not afraid to call them out if they
do do something wrong so I think that's
important too because we can't be like
bullied around by them either we have to
like and also it's like if you yell
about everything then the stuff you do
yell then just it doesn't matter so it's
a mix of all that like yeah and there's
a lot of that where
people I mean we all know the people on
Twitter who when they when they cry foul
your immediate reaction isn't like oh no
what did Apple do this time it's kind of
like all right let's dig in and see cuz
sometimes it is legitimate sometimes
it's just like you're screaming over
nothing no fully that exactly and so
yeah like you said it is good that other
people are doing it cuz it's not bad to
have that necessarily but yeah it's just
not what I want to be doing I don't
think it's the best way to get to it's
definitely not the best way to change
opinions I know that for sure like yeah
right sometimes it's the best way to
make change it's like violence right I
don't like violence I that is not
something that comes naturally to me uh
by any means uh but I can also
appreciate that sometimes in extreme
circumstances I'm not advocating so I'm
just saying like it can uh precipitate
change right like clearly and so uh so
yeah I it's just something
yeah I I find very endearing about your
role in this whole Saga that we're all
going through right now is uh I find you
sorry I know I'm it's very uncomfortable
to have Heap Praise heaped on you keep
keep you out yeah I love it you're like
no not at all uh it's it's just
something I find yeah it makes me really
want to listen to people who have
a tempered mindset about things and who
will call
out postives in their enemies so to
speak again not saying that you're
saying there that you're enemy but it
can easily get turned into these like
these lines of two sides of a battle uh
and I feel like it it feels like you all
have intentionally kind of avoided you
know that in a way which is surprising
given where you're at and all this
anyway sorry that was a weird de side
you brought it up and I wanted to make
sure we talked about that cuz I just I
find it fascinating no thank you for
thank you for saying that I just I'm
glad that is appreciated because yeah we
do try really hard when we're in the
middle of all this and sometimes we do
have to restrain ourselves there have
been plenty of times I've been more
livid than what's come out
professionally from us and Y yeah I have
to imagine show so uh and so I guess
this was not necessarily your first time
dealing with this cuz you did previously
but it was not it wasn't your uh
Enterprise license certificate in the
past so it was a little more indirect
but this was pretty directly like aimed
you but you figured out a mechanism to
deal with this it sounds like and then
yeah we've not too interesting just like
a whole different authentication
mechanism at a reverse engineer and then
but once we did that honestly Apple
didn't really mess with us again after
that so it was it was just kind of us
existing on the side in this weird
unofficial world and so Delta again was
still totally free at this time yep
totally free but you was your entire
income coming from contract work then or
did you find a way to sort of get
support for for this whole project so it
was before I commit went to altstar
full-time and working on Delta it was I
was talking to my at the time roommate
Shane Gil who became my co-found later
and he was pitching me on the idea of
patreon cuz my idea honestly was like to
put this out there Al S as a tool and
then kind of move on like like I would
support it but like it wouldn't be like
my main job and Shane was the one that
was like hey there's like real demand
like in the Creator economy people
really want to support independent
creators right now like it just like
yeah because he was like he was
supporting a few and he was like for
YouTubers especially and so I kind of
like was thinking about that and I like
you know what maybe I could try just
make a patreon and so when I launched
alt store at the time I also launched my
own patreon and the way I like tried to
give benefits or incentivize it was if
you join it you get access to the beta
versions of our apps so Delta and
eventually that's such a good I feel
like that's a really good mechanism
because it's like yeah your most sort of
devoted the ones who are getting the
most value out of it um they're going to
be the most interested in that for most
people it's fine it works really well I
think for certain types of apps but
right for so many reasons of people
don't want to pay for emulators there's
like a lot of weird stuff with it in
general so it was like I Delta just was
always going to be free like I just keep
that simple there's cultural thing there
right yeah and then there's other stuff
like I don't like the idea of having
like a paid version of app because it
means all your users or majority of
users are not getting the best
experience like it just like if you have
a premium version only a subset is going
to ever use that and that's just like
unfortunate for me it's like as a
developer I want my users to like be
using the best version of the product
and so this yes has just been an
interesting way of doing that where
everyone gets the features event like
the stuff I put out for free to everyone
is polished it's tested I'm okay with it
I but if you want to donate to us you
can just have early access to the new
features and yeah I honestly think
that's a really good structure for apps
like this and we also I like it and and
again with the emulator community in
particular it's like early access to
hacky or or less tested things is a high
value thing exactly yeah um it might it
probably wouldn't work for you know your
calendar app or your uh knows personal
CRM app well but like those are things
where people it's like they need to be
solid for most people M um yeah I'm like
open GES 3.0 try it out let me know if
it breaks your games or not and
something and people like cool yeah
that's almost part of the fun of that
Community right is like trying and
things breaking and everything exactly
yeah that's cool so okay so so you had a
way to monetize it at some point or
maybe right away you this became sort of
your full-time yeah right away so once I
launched y okay
and so at first it's it's literally alt
store is just a Delta launcher yeah how
quickly or did that change to being
there's more things that you can make
available the the beta version of alt
store I did the same thing with alt
store that could install like more apps
so is Delta could be installed in the
free version but if you joined the
patreon you could actually just s load
any IPA you found it wasn't like sources
wasn't built like you couldn't browse it
but if you just downloaded an app file
you could install it and so that we did
but we officially released like that
functionality I think like several
months like six months later or so and
then that at that point it was a tool it
was you could find Delta in the app or
you could download apps outside like on
the web where are people
finding they have to be unsigned ipas
like I mean they could be signed or
unsigned I
resign but yes there an IPA out there in
the world where are those coming from
other than I mean when I was in the
Windows phone world I know people were
taking cracked ipas of famous apps so
they could like build clones or
something but other than that like what
was there a marketpl or not a
Marketplace but was there a community of
people releasing ipas like this yeah
like a surprisingly a large amount
because since GBA came out and I gave up
there would have been like this black
market of Enterprise certificates being
used and that was how people were doing
it before was with his Enterprise
certificates so I wasn't part of that
that but then I came in with alt store
then people were like oh this is better
than this weird Enterprise certificate
and so there were just a bunch of like
Edge case apps that built up yeah
exactly and eventually You released at
least one more of your own CU clip
wasent came out yeah that was in in the
original alt store at some point right
not original as in when it first
launched but before alt store Pop It was
supposed to be there at literal launch
but then there was there was a last
minute bug that made it not work and so
I had to pull it and that's what killed
me cuz I wanted to launch alt store with
Delta and clip cuz I was like it is a
store yeah and then I had to launch it
with Delta like but whatever it was fine
and like in time it was fine and a real
quick aside on clip uh mostly just me
begging anybody at Apple who's listening
to please for the love of God make it
possible to to put these on the store
what is clip clip is my clipboard
manager and all it does is it just runs
in the background and listens for
whatever or you copy something and then
it shows your little alert say would
like to save this to your clipboard and
if you just tap that alert saves your
clipboard that's it and it's just so use
I use a clipboard manager on my Mac all
the time yes and for anybody who doesn't
know clipboard managers are basically I
mean whenever you copy something it goes
into your clipboard and if you copy
something else it overrides what goes
into your clipboard at the most basic
level all a clipboard manager is doing
is saying every time you copy something
it adds it to a list instead of just
overwriting it and that way you can
actually access previously copied text
and it's one of those tools that like
probably most developers listening have
used some in some capacity but it's like
once you get used to the idea of a
clipboard manager running your computer
feels completely broken not having it uh
because the amount of times I'll copy
two different things so I can paste two
different things somewhere is
ridiculously frequent and I actually use
uh I use uh paste it's a clipboard
manager on the Mac and it has an IOS app
uh but I but it it doesn't integrate the
way that yours do you need that it's
that's the feature is it needs to be
automatic whenever you copy something
it's now and clip isn't per that's the
the original version of clip that I was
going to launch an ALT store was perfect
it ran in the background and you didn't
need to inter interact at all it just
would save everything in the background
and what was the mechanism you were
using for that that was a combination of
I use I used like a silent audio track
just to run the background using the
music thing I stole that from pbot from
back in the day on iPhone and then I
used it was an audio unit I think
extension to like one of the weird app
extensions and that had permission to
access the clipboard in the background
so I had this weird extension that I
would basically funnel audio data into
that was like Json data and then I would
be like okay read the clipboard and it
would send it back to clip but it worked
it was perfect and that was what I was
going to launch and then that's a
functionality that broke right before
cuz an iOS 13 Apple released iOS 13 that
broke that bug and I was like well now
clip doesn't work at all what was the
battery impact of that um I didn't do
any tests it didn't seem to be that big
a deal in practice for me was
massively obviously it'd be better to
have a native API for it but for sure
absolutely but it like yeah it was good
enough but then but then you didn't
launch it with that version but yeah
yeah because it it didn't work at all so
I was like H had to hold it back until I
found another workr and that's the new
notification it shows a notification
when it the clipboard changes and you
tap that that was so you have to
actually like engage with it at least
it's possible a notification extension
does have access the clipboard because
it's in the foreground that's the
differentiator if an if your extension
or app is in the foreground it can
access the clipboard if it's in the
backround okay ah interesting y yeah so
uh if you take nothing away from this
whole episode you know more important
than any of the accomplishments that
Riley has done it's that clipboard
managers should exist on iOS and in some
capacity and we should all pressure
Apple yeah like I've used when I use my
Windows PC for programming as a built-in
clipboard manager I'm like wow so nice
Windows yeah itself yeah oh I remember
it being built into like Visual Studio
but no yeah it's just a full systemwide
I'm like well it's easy yeah it is it
yeah it is easy it's just just check the
box to implement it shouldn't be that
crazy though yeah it feels like the type
of thing that it just the problem is it
has to be built by the platform yeah
exactly anyway okay yeah so clip
eventually came but that's an app built
by you uh people can download their own
ipas uh from wherever and run those but
uh when or did you ever get third
parties basically releasing their apps
through the alt store and what was that
process um that process was basically we
discovering what are the most popular
ipas people were installing at the time
and we're like oh you know what we
should try to reach out to some of these
and have them like officially like in
the store so that like the next
like okay now it's an IPA inster we want
a store we want to be able to you
receive updates like you get automatic
updates and you can view store pages so
then that was our next step in out store
and I think that came maybe a few months
later a year later or so and we launched
with like dolphin the Dolphin Emulator
oh yeah and like and UTM was one of our
first which one's UTM I don't know oh
dolphin is for the Wii right yeah
dolphin's for the Wii and stuff the
utm's for PC it's a PC emulator so you
can run Windows oh wow okay and stuff
and so we're like hey look you can yeah
run Wii you can run Windows all
throughout store and and so that was
like our first batch of apps again just
showing stuff like that and then that's
what we were for then a while so you had
just kind of a collection of sort of
Fringe apps that couldn't get through
app review um but it worked and it was
there's obviously limitations especially
if you're on a non-developer free
account but like you had a mechanism to
make this possible and you had a
uh patreon basee that could support you
continuing to build on it for a while
and then uh the world yes exploded uh or
at least the the European Union exploded
so what just walk us through that story
that led to essentially alt store pal
yeah so much and so we're I'm working on
alt store honest and the like I'm seeing
the political wins I'm seeing that
Europe's investigating I'm that America
is investig app was like in 20 2020 2021
yeah and Japan and Korea and it's kind
of everywhere and so I see it all coming
but I'm also like I'm burnt out like at
this point I truly am so burnt out
unable like I'm not I was not able to do
much at all for like almost a full year
cuz I was just like so exhausted from
alt store and like handling everything
and it was just me at the time and I
really was like
feeling the end of it and I was like had
to I really felt like is this something
I want to stick with do I have the
energy to keep this up and I was like so
I saw that the political winds were
changing I saw that this could be
something in the future and so I was
like H I want to stick this out but I
don't know if I can do this alone and so
that's when I was like realized I need
to have Shane come on board like he so
he'd been with me like this whole time
he we' always like talk together through
ideas and everything and what's been the
big what's been the big help with
bringing somebody on then is that on the
development side is that on the just
having another person to absorb the
stress of everything with you no yeah
having another person is the number one
thing cuz I I was pretty depressed as
well during this like year because I had
all these like all store was doing so
well but I was doing it myself and so it
was like very isolating and I would be
at home be like I'm doing my own thing
but everyone else just has a normal jobs
and it felt just alone and so him coming
on board to just be there with me
through it all all like probably the
hugest for my mental health just gave me
so much I think that's I think that's a
I I almost said not talked about I think
people talk about it plenty probably but
like it is one of the weird things about
being especially a solo Indie developer
is uh I I think it's maybe David Smith I
forgot who it is somebody's talked about
this where like you do a launch and it's
like it feels like this big thing and
you've been building up to it for months
you know where you have this
anticipation feeling and
and and obviously there's a version of
it where it fails and that's sad and
everybody can imagine that but the one
that's the weirdest is when it succeeds
the numbers are big you have a bunch of
people reply on Twitter to say you know
good job and then you know you go pick
up your kids from school or you go
whatever and you're like doing laundry
and cleaning your dishes that evening
and it's just like normal and there's
almost
something deeply depressing about that
no it really was yeah it makes your life
feel almost not meaningless that's the
wrong word but it's like yeah you build
this thing up in your head so much
because it could go wrong and then when
it goes right it's almost sad and Simply
Having
a having a group of people that you can
share in the excitement with whether
that's in person or even just a friend
group of other people who do the same
thing who can get excited with you it's
surprising how much of a difference that
makes cuz at a company you get that
naturally yes um and on your own you
just don't and I yeah so I but that's
exactly it I just had to learn that
myself like 2020 basically was a great
year for alt store and then 2021 I
crashed cuz it was like that I just was
man I like it was such a ride and wave
and then I just was by myself still
nothing had changed I was like yeah your
actual life wasn't really actually
different even though it felt like it
should be so yeah so but so yeah
bringing him on board changed all that
the original pitch was to move to New
Zealand together I was like let's go
let's do this let go back I want to go
back to like my home country amazing it
was in the middle of Co though and they
did not yeah I was to say New Zealand
famously was very open I mean I was
wanting to get in that bubble I was like
I want in there but then yeah that's
true yeah so then Shane I'm a citizen
Shane is not so he was not able to come
so we moved to Dallas Texas instead to
my other home just as exciting the New
Zealand of the Midwest you know that's
what they say so do you consider it the
Midwest I mean yeah that is what we say
here yeah Midwest really oh man I'm I'm
going to do my best not to go off really
far on this but I'm fascinated by this
topic I have family in Oklahoma MH and
every time I talk to them I'm like what
region do you consider yourself in and
they're like uh Oklahoma like I don't
know and I was like what do you call
that it's not the South and Texas in my
head has always been Texas yeah I know I
mean yeah we are pretty Texas but if I
were to describe where we are like like
the Midwest whatever you'll say the
Midwest oh that's super interesting to
me okay anyway yes we'll move on uh but
uh okay so you you got somebody on board
uh which I can already predict was
unbelievably uh necessary for you to
survive the insanity that happened so
then after you brought him on board we
how did the insanity go we just were
like okay we had like we're like let's
hit the ground running we knew this was
going to happen soon so we just like
worked together we were super like
efficient we got we figured out our
whole like work schedule and everything
and so then we spent like a good and
this is going to happen soon meaning
some sort of opening up of the App Store
the dma was still like about to be
passed and so we were just preparing for
whatever that was and then it just fast
forward to then the dma Bas finally was
passed like the actual law came out was
passed and then that's when we were like
okay this is it before Apple said
anything we were like okay we know this
is now a real thing and so we really dma
for anybody who missed all this
uh which I is totally understandable cuz
it was a lot uh was the European Union
passed a law to basically well it had a
lot of different things that targeted a
lot of different big tech companies but
with regards to this story and apple
specifically it meant that at least in
some capacity Apple had to open up the
app store to third party apps sort of
yeah what that necessarily meant nobody
fully knew yet but it was going to
happen and so that's that's the stage
set for you know something's going to
happen and you're trying to prepare for
it yeah exactly and so so yeah we were
prepared for that and then I was fast
forward to the real when everything
really changed was last year when Apple
announced how they were going to comply
cuz we knew that there was just going to
be a way to install apps outside the App
Store and we had no idea what that would
looked like we honestly were hoping for
not third party app stores we were
hoping that it was just going to be like
apple be like you can just sideload from
the web or something and then we were
like oh we'll turn alt store and like
this discovery platform not whole store
but then Apple announces in January nope
okay third party app stores a full thing
and you got to have all these ridiculous
requirements like the standby letter of
credit you got to have a subsidiary in
like Europe and we're like oh my God and
so that was January 25th and the law get
into effect March 5th and we were like
okay we have a little over a month to do
all of this to build to turn alt store
into a full app store to get this money
to like foring Corporation in Europe and
that so yeah that was probably the most
stressful like month of the year cuz we
were just like what the hell are we
doing and man just and thank God for
Shane he did so much of like the
business he was able to get a standby
letter credit we found people at Morgan
Stanley who believed in us like and like
just working so hard to do that and we
did that for a month and then we were
coming up on the March 5th deadline
that's when the law went into effect and
apple had to comply and so Apple then
had this Workshop in like Cork Ireland
for alternative marketplaces to like go
and get help and this is like the two
weeks before March 5th and so me and
Shane were like okay you know what we're
getting close to like we're we're pretty
close to launch we 't working we should
apply we should go to this court or we
should go to this lab get any help we
need and so that's kind of what we did
and by the time we got there it was like
Fe the end of February and we were had
everything working like I had I had
update I had worked on alt store it
worked as an App Store with the new
Marketplace kit framework that Apple
released and so basically we showed up
day one and we're like cool we're ready
to launch and they were not wri for that
and it was very clear that apple had no
idea that we were this close to being
ready to launch and they just flat out
we're not ready in time for the deadline
and so that
then was the whole bit where we were
like we're in Europe now the app is
ready to launch we have all the things
that we need from Apple and Apple's like
we're going to take our time we're going
to see what we need to do here and so we
did a lot of stupid stuff during this
time because but God we're just getting
so frustrated CU Apple was just delaying
like trying to delay us and we were like
this is not fair we are here we're ready
to launch you the law says you have to
be ready by March 5th Apple so we were
pretty pissed off we so then like a week
like no the day like the week of March
5th we sent an email at Tim Cook cred
federi Phil Schiller we just said like
bluntly we are here in Europe we are
ready to launch y'all are holding us up
please approve our app so we can launch
on the deadline and we sent it to them
and then sure enough the next day we got
some progress happening on us and then
we also got a Stern talking to from our
contacts at the lab saying not to email
Tim Cook again but we're like it's the
thing only thing that works like apple
don't never run to the Press thing like
well except for when you have to this is
the beginning of us learning that Apple
like again we want to be working with
apple and we've learned apple is not
wanting to give an inch at all and I
think that's dumb of them but whatever
so we're like fine we'll email Tim Cook
they finally notorized our test app but
then they still were holding up alt
store and we stuck in Europe so we're
just there for what ends up two months
just trying to launch yeah you were kind
of bouncing all over the place right and
weren't you going to like EU is it
parliaments you were going to like
special sessions they were putting on
and stuff right because basically we
were there and
then we got this email from the European
commission saying hey you oh we're
having this Workshop in Brussels would
you like to join and we were like you
know what since we're here in Europe why
not let's just like join this thing
that's kind of why like what started
this whole thing so then we traveled to
Europe then we were at this Workshop I
asked Apple questions and whatever and
yes we it was a whole
ordeal yeah and we we're like running
low on time otherwise I would want to
dig into the Press frenzy that you were
sort of in the middle of cuz you were
being quoted
in papers of record and like your faces
and videos everywhere yeah it was such a
surreal time just because yeah like we
were we were just we weren't doing
anything all day in Europe just waiting
for Apple so then we would like fill our
times talking to reporters or like just
doing whatever because we're like we
literally can't do anything else and it
was a whole yes frustrating part I
hearing the beginning of this I didn't
realize you were just completely on your
own until right before all this happened
oh yeah and it's like I can't imagine
that like uh doing that on your own I
mean it also sounds like he was just
really good at all the business stuff
too but like even just having a person
with you through all this must have been
there's no way I could have done this
the only thing that kept you going yeah
cuz it's just us two backpacking through
Europe I have my iMac though cuz I
brought that I wasn't yeah I've seen
pictures of you in cafes with an iMac Is
that real yeah cuz I I love my iMac it's
great I have a carrying case for it and
it's cuz I don't need to carry another
separate screen it's amazing but then
I'm now I'm traveling through Europe
literally with a iMac sorry a freaking
iMac and you know what like just
whatever just so ridiculous but we don't
at this point we're like don't care
crazy yeah okay but
eventually uh it gets through right what
was what was the deal
there so again we're waiting we're
finally and then it's a Friday night
we're at tily this amusement park in
Denmark in Copenhagen and we're about to
get on this roller coaster and I get
this email saying the App Store rules
guidelines have changed and emulators
are now allowed in the app store oh
right
and we're
like this was the most caught off guard
I had been this entire time like was
this move by Apple cuz I and it so
surreal again we're about to get in this
roller coaster I'm like really I'm like
what like this is our whole thing like
we're about get on the roller coaster
did you get out of line we got and but
my first Rea my reactions basic me and
Shane had different reactions Shane was
more of like what does this mean like
what like this is our whole bit and I
was honest like
this means that we really got to them
like if they changed the App Store rules
to allow ulators that means they're
afraid of us and so that gave me like
the motivation like okay let's do this
if they want to allow it in the App
Store let's put Delta in the App Store
let's use that to get like notoriety for
us and so then we were like that was the
plan and so and so I was giddy that
roller coaster I was like Wow Delta is
going to be in the App Store like and I
just couldn't believe it and it was so
amazing
what a surreal just memory to have on
that roller coaster so like just like
yeah my mind going through everything
and like wow this is like everything
I've dreamed of and so yep that happened
and then after they approved it guess
what Apple was like okay you have to go
ahead to launch alt store now yeah and
we're like they waited until the
leverage for why everybody would
download it went away and that that your
fear thing that's at least my
interpretation of those events is when
they realized that they were going to
have to let this through and they
probably knew how much demand there was
going to be for an emulator and a nice
emulator that has already been proven to
be
popular and they didn't want a really
really popular app that you can only get
through third party store to drive loads
of people especially younger people to
normalize downloading these third party
apps that they don't really want people
or sorry third party stores that they
don't really want
people downloading in the first place M
uh and so they tried to cut it off at
the knees by making that app available
on the app store anyway yeah exactly and
so and also say this was the most
impressed I was with apple as like a
strategic
move it's a very like I respect you
moment I truly was like man that is a
very good move of y'all and I'm very if
you didn't do it it then turns the like
uh the pr against you right mhm it would
have been an easy La for us that but
then they did that I like Kudos apple
and again like I I like a good comp
competitor move I like to be challenged
a little bit I was like okay good for
you I'm proud of y'all for doing that
just did not think you would but so then
whatever and then we then yeah so I
think the next week we then finally
launched alt store pal officially with
Delta in Europe and then in the App
Store outside of the EU and ALT store
pal the naming just Chef's
uh pal meaning for those who don't know
uh if you're in North America and have
never dealt with this like that is the
what's the actual name it's like the
convention for the uh man like the video
format like yeah it's like the format
for just like standard def video
broadcasts so in the states it's ntsc
right and in Europe it was pal and like
pal is 50 frames a second instead of 60
frames a second and a couple interlacing
details and stuff but yeah that's just
such a great that was such a great name
for like this version of the alt store
thank you no we were once we came up
with that cuz we were like we need to
have a way of differentiating between
existing alt store new alt store I
didn't want to call it European alt
store I didn't want to call it new alt
store but then we were like like region
locking and that's what led to the oh
Pal games yeah so good pretty and so
good at the gaming level like way of
thinking about it too no and then also
say we were talking to the verge at this
time like CU we had like a launch
article ready to go with them yeah and
oh my they really wanted to spoil the
name alster pal ahead of time they were
like asking us so like can we please say
it and we're like no we're sa no we're
saving that that's our s you can't
announce that they really wanted that
scoop that's amazing and so we're like
no no no no no we're saving and we we
yeah held firm on that one I'm so glad
we did because like no it's got to be a
surprise name people can't expect it
that's great so yeah and then Delta
itself uh you know it came out on the
App Store and it I mean just exploded
like it was the most popular app on the
store for weeks right it for 2 weeks it
was the most popular app in the app
store how I have to assume like you
don't have servers or anything right so
at least there wasn't that yeah yeah but
well right right for for Delta but I
have to imagine your support like you
were getting just an ungodly amount of
email and everything right yes what was
that like well that was Shane I did not
have to be the one with it but what
happened was we came home Shane
immediately went to Coachella cuz we
came home the week before Coachella and
Shane want Coachella Music Festival if
anyone doesn't know and he was like yeah
I want he wanted to go and so he did
that for the like the weekend after
lunch and so I was like holding the fort
of everything I'm just like making sure
everything landed and then he he came
home and to like say I'm sorry for
leaving for the weekend he just like did
support for like a week straight of just
like going through all the emails we got
good most I most support was actually
alt store we did not get a lot of
support for Delta it was primarily and
to be fair alt store because there was
there were a lot of launch makes sense
but just the scale I have to imagine was
cuz like what are the numbers you were
or have you shared that oh yeah for like
how many downloads and stuff 15 million
I think the last I checked for Delta
like that's an astronomical amount of
people no it's it's it's yeah absurd and
and yeah in the first days it was in the
millions and so yes there were
immediately a lot but yes so they're not
that many critical issues in Delta
itself which I felt really good about
but I this ALS it had been around for
years and so it wasn't like a 1.0 app
alt store very much ALT store pal the
back end very much was a 1.0 and well I
mean Apple's back end was very much a
1.0 if if that right and there's it's
still buggy like there's an it's like
updating alt store pal is still broken
on Apple's end and it's very frustrating
and like I I mean I work for a company
that is all about working with Apple's
storit apis which are foundational to a
huge amount of how they make money yep
uh and that's something they really
really want people to use I can't
imagine uh what the marketplace apis are
like uh when it's you know I don't want
to throw around malicious compliance uh
flippantly but it's certainly not
something they're excited to no it's
certainly not and that's what I say it's
you can tell it's it's not that they're
trying to make it bad but it's like it's
okay actually they I don't want to throw
hate out I do think they did a lot and
the the framework and the stuff they
provided actually is pretty extensive
and I do think they are trying but yes
it is still very buggy and is it would
you say that this is one of those deals
where it's like the company
strategically at high levels obviously
wants limits that are going to make your
life difficult but the engineers down at
the level of people who are building
this for you they're still well there's
still people at Apple who have pride in
their work and want to make something
good is that is that accurate yes very
much yeah yeah yeah so I mean that's
that's good at least um and to be clear
I feel similarly at the the storit level
they do lots of things that are great
it's not like it's just there's often
times things that are frustrating way
that you're like how is a company of
this scale UHA still running into these
kind of issues but you know whatever
yeah software right yly um so the that
all went you know the way that it went
um but then there like that came out and
it was a huge story obviously you had
lots of support but I assume that waned
off uh over time yeah um but then over
the year there's still just been every
time a new app comes out or what seemed
like was happening often a new app was
trying to come out and the uh
notarization service which was not
supposed to be app review which we
haven't really discussed here yeah yeah
turned to kind of actually be app riew
and there has been lots of just flareups
throughout the year of events happening
uh we don't have to go through like each
one of those like people can read The
Verge or whatever but like what has that
experience been like because you
traveling through Europe and going
through this Whirlwind experience
culminating in you riding a roller
coaster and you know seeing stars in the
future ahead of you exactly that is like
this weird wild ride but now you're at
home and you're work working but there's
still these occasional blasts that come
up how do you deal with those as they
come in like are you used to it at this
point it's just a thing that
happens maybe yeah kind of I don't want
yeah just we've kind of settled into
that flow of have especially we have to
split our time between Delta and ALT
store and so that's kind of like what we
do mostly so I'll work on Delta like for
a little bit to get an update out and
then we'll focus on alt store and try to
see okay what are some apps out there
that we can promote or something like
that and so we've been doing back and
forth but I'll actually most of our
biggest opportunities have just happened
like yeah one of the biggest like
fortnite went yeah yeah that was what
November that was later last year right
yeah that was or this was back in June
July or was it over the summer okay yeah
yeah but either way fortnite famously uh
did their whole own you know kind of
uh throw some shade at Apple got into a
big fight and they pulled everything
from both Apple and Google um and so
they weren't available at all now they
set up their own store as well right so
there is a fortnite store in the EU that
you could call a competitor in a sense
it's the same kind of conceptual thing
as alt store except it's focused on
games and fortnite's available there but
then epic invested in you all right yes
and then they brought fortnite to alt
store as well yeah and that was a whole
thing because I was be going in we had
the same opinions towards epic I think
most people in the Apple Community were
like oh my God y'all are just like
yelling about all this stuff you're
doing this so stupidly like why are you
being so aggressive and so basically we
it was like June and then we just got
this email out of the blue from them
saying hey we would love to talk we saw
your work in alt store we'd love to see
if there any way we could work together
and my first thought was no like what
what are they why what do they want from
us do they want us to put Delta in Epic
we're not going to do that but Shane was
like you know what maybe we should like
give it a chance or like see yeah yeah
worth a worth a discussion yeah but the
thing that really changed it was right
around this time Apple rejected UTM the
the PC emulator from altstar pal yes and
we were like what like this is the first
time they had like blocked an app and we
were like yeah and for anybody listening
and Confused by what we mean by rejected
because yeah like there is no app review
process for a thirdparty store that
Apple doesn't run but there is a system
called notarization which everybody kind
of agreed this seems like it's a good
thing that they still have because it's
it's similar to what they have on the
Mac which is like you have to send your
app binary essentially to Apple and they
run a bunch of Security checks as well
as keep track of like
the I don't know what they're keeping
track of some sort of ID on it basically
so they have a kill switch so they can
kill access to the OS to even run it um
but it's basically just a security layer
it's like you can you can put whatever
you want there's torrents on the Mac
that are notorized like it's it's a it's
it's not a way for them to do their
normal app review thing it's supposed to
be a way for them to just make sure that
there's some security on iOS still so
everybody thought that was okay but then
what you all were running into with UTM
was were rejecting apps not because of
security reasons but just because they
just don't want it they don't like them
and this is yeah this is when we were
like again we were giving benefit out
this whole time and this was the first
time we're like apple we've kind of
trusted that you're going to not do this
kind of thing and so that we and we
talked to them for a bit and then we
talked to them at dub actually at dub I
reached to out to like the app riew team
I had a lab with them and I explained
hey this should be really loud and then
like a couple weeks later I got a call
from app review and on and they called
saying we have some great news we've
decided to allow UTM into the App Store
as well as a prove it for you wait what
yeah and then I was like lit on the
phone I was
like and again I was like it was
delivered perfectly the person on the
phone just said it in the perfect half I
was like oh man I can't believe this oh
it's like the uh it's like a get out or
something smiling and like creepy but
again I was like I can't believe but I
respect this delivery wait I don't
remember that so is UTM on the App Store
it is in the App Store now because they
didn't want to go to us I completely
missed this so they wow that's so
bizarre and so and yeah the second time
in like a few months that apple had
changed our app store rules because we
had an app in alt store that was like a
cool idea and so that's what's crazy is
that was one that existed well I guess
sort of delta in your previous alt store
yes exactly but obviously the mechanism
was way different and it's it's the same
thing it's like they don't want people
normalizing the behavior of like yeah go
download third party stores Y and so
anything that threatens them Ah that's
so wild didn't they have to limit UTM
I'm starting to remember this wasn't
there a couple things that they had to
change so the yeah the UTM and the
original store use jit like just in time
compilation and that's for technical
reasons not possible in the alt store
pal version okay or in the App Store App
Store and out store pal can't use okay
so they're the same on both yeah so it's
just a slower UTM but and so oh but the
reason I brought this up is they called
me and I was this like when one of my
most pissed I was like they like they
can't do this I was like I don't care if
they approve an out foral store and then
change the App Store rules that's
competition that's how it works holding
it up it is the fact that we weren't
allowed to have it in the first place
and so I was pissed off and so that's
when I was like Shane okay no we're
talking to Epic now like I'm tired of
trying to work with apple like they are
just taking advantage of us they like
cuz like we had been so good and yeah
back to the Brussels thing we emailed
them the question that we were going to
ask them ahead of time we were like Hey
we're going to call you you're not
trying to do Goa like we were like hey
we're working with you we want to have a
productive like way and so this is when
I was first like okay Apple's not
working with us let's talk to Epic and
then we talked to Epic and they really
were from the standpoint of hey we
really just need people to be on
alternative app stores and to do that
this needs to be normalized and so they
just that is their entire goal yeah was
and they were like so we want fortnite
can would you be interested in having
fortnite on your store and we're like
you know I think we much so yeah we can
open to that that's perfect and then and
then they were like and you know would
it help if you didn't have to have that
$150 subscription oh I should say at the
time about that cuz Apple charges us 50
cents for every download of alt store
pal for a reason called The Core
technology fee and we couldn't afford
that cuz we're just based off donations
and so we had to pass that on consumers
so we charged A50 to cover also for
Delta the 50 Cent fee and tax and
everything yeah and so we charged that
but epic then said would you get more
downloads if it was free and we were
just like probably yeah I think so and
so they then were like sure then we'll
give you we'll cover your CTF we just
want you to be able to exist like as
easily as possible and I do believe that
they do truly believe that exactly like
there should just be more just like
apple you're dealing with a company that
has strategic goals and it's like they
are highly incentivized to make it
normalized to uh to download third party
app stores and make it a thing that
people are used to using and so any way
they can reduce that friction helps them
long term exactly and so now we're so
they're just like cool we want to put
your apps or our apps in your store and
they didn't care about us putting our
apps in their store so we're like sounds
good to us we will take your money
that's crazy so what was that like when
that happened was there just like a was
there a big impact on alt store
downloads or did that change anything
for sure the fact of it being free was
just the biggest thing by far yeah which
I mean I understand I it was always dumb
that you had to pay for allar even
though it was like only A50 I know
that's like a frustration like I totally
get it and so that was wasn't that you
talked about the question that you
emailed Apple ahead of time wasn't that
the question you asked was basically
like hey I was a student I want to put
this stuff out there for free y you're
creating a mechanism that makes it where
it would cost me millions of dollars if
this becomes popular what's the
mechanism and if I remember correctly
their response was very like that's a
good point like we really want to work
with you on that it's almost like
because I didn't call them out on it no
exactly it's back to the productive like
that's how I thought this would work
better I thought if me and us and apple
are working together this is better for
both of us apple does not feel that way
and it's yeah and like to counter what I
said earlier about the being cordial
it's like that's an example where you
give giving them that question ahead of
time probably meant they could prepare a
question that sounded really good yeah
and because I remember the reaction
being pretty positive to like oh wow
Apple actually like responded not
callously like we were used to but it's
probably because they were prepared for
it yeah but it's like I we wanted to
have a win for both of us that's what we
that was our dream like hey we can both
win it's not a zero some game here Apple
like we just want to be the tiny little
store on the side with the apps that you
don't want like the apps you are
literally rejecting we will take we're
not trying to steal but yeah and so
we're working together and it seemed to
be fine but yes and that slowly fell
apart and around so then we started
working with epic more and post working
with epic we have not been working with
apple near this closely and for just a
mix of reasons I think they hate it and
I'm als we like yeah again we were just
like so really we learned that were
taking advantage of us so we stopped
trying to reach out to them yeah I mean
it's like any business relationship is
built on trust
and uh they burned it the sad thing yeah
the sad thing yeah they burned it and
epic we went in thinking like
distrusting and then they to credit what
everything they have backed up
everything they said they have not tried
to like screw us over and it's and it's
hard so I'm like I wanted to be aligned
with apple I didn't want to be aligned
with epic this is not what I was trying
to do but it's like this is the reality
it's apple is not wanting to play along
and whatever I guess the last thing then
to kind of touch on is the last flare up
I alluded to recently that happened
yesterday so these episodes I don't
release this like right after they come
out so this will all be old news and I'm
sure there'll be five more layers to the
story by the time it comes out but uh
and also this is a very like
familyfriendly show so just so you know
we're going to be talking about an adult
oriented app so I'll have chapter
markers around it feel free to skip it I
mean we're not going to be cussing or
talking anything really explicit but
just so you know that's that's happening
uh so correct me if I'm wrong my
understanding of the story is uh a new
app has been launched on alt store pile
which is called bathtub hot tub and it's
basically like a a porn app right uh
which famously is not allowed on the App
Store at all uh unless it's not the
primary part of your app as many people
pointed out over the last 24 hours
Reddit
is basically a porn app that also has a
bunch of other stuff on top of it that's
bigger so Apple lets them through um and
then of course like Safari itself can
get access to adult content just super
easily so it's it's kind of a a bit of a
like silly thing but you know it is part
of the App Store and I do think as a
parent it's like I get it they want the
App Store to be of a certain level of
trustworthiness doesn't stop them from
putting casino apps for children in
there but and I get it too I agree yeah
and and having in a third party app
store is a good opportunity for these
things to exist in a separated way or
whatever um but yeah that's kind of the
the foundation as this came out and then
Apple on as you'd expect freaked out
about it but the thing that I'm guessing
you didn't expect is the way they
freaked out about it was they super
honed in on the fact that your press
release was using the words we've gotten
or apple has approved this app it's the
first app that they've approved and I'm
I'm putting your words in your mouth so
correct me but my under my guess is that
when you say approved you mean unlike
UTM or these other stories that we just
talked about where they were denying the
notarization process they approved the
notarization which means we actually
could let it through yes that is was
like they're making it sound like we
approved this and we did not because we
want to protect your children is that is
that a correct sort of yeah pretty good
just summary of the whole thing and
you're right that I we did not expect
that strong a response cuz yeah so to
back up yeah We Knew by saying Apple
approved that it was Apple's not going
to like that but the reason we did this
it's kind of like the same back in
November Apple rejected mini vmac a Mac
emulator from our store again and once
again I was pretty pissed off I was like
apple you cannot do this this one is
just a legal like I'm sorry and so we've
been talking to the EC about this but I
was like if Apple wants to be abusing
theorization process like this we need
to like use it against them like if they
want to be inserting themselves in it
they got to put their name on these
things I see they're because they people
don't realize that they are involved in
this they're getting away with making
these decisions and no one and with no
scrutiny and so it's a have your cake
and eat it too it's like if you're going
to use notarization to say we are
allowing this or we're not allowing this
based on our own decisions we're going
to highlight the fact that all right
well then that meant that you were okay
with this one to your by your own and so
that was the motivation it was we were
protesting them abusing notarization and
I thought it was funny because I was
like because it was true I was like it
is approved I think it's a pretty funny
statement I know Apple's going to hate
it but I don't care that's a pretty
that's a pretty good like uh PR slide of
hand I was I was happy with it I thought
so and most people liked it we did learn
that I did not expect people just
thought we were lying and just thought
we made up that Apple approved it and
that was basically what that was
probably the just the miscalculation on
us was we're so in the Weeds on this we
for kind of forgot that people may
actually think that we're just lying
about like making up lies about this
that it's just a complete PR trying to
get attention move exactly so that was
an interesting thing that we had like
figure out but no it was yeah my
favorite thing is we sent this out to
like maybe like a few we like the Verge
and Tech crunch ahead of time saying
that we're going to lunches and then
Apple sent out their response too
everyone like this like the stupidest
thing like we got so many press emails
within the next like hour after Apple
sent out that blast cuz everyone was
just like what like what happened like
what is Apple talking about and so they
reached out and we're like why we we're
like shocked like why when you do
something like that Did you sort of have
a Playbook like were you prepared for
all right they're going to get mad
here's our sort of like standard
statement or was your statement your
original statement and that's basically
it it was our original statement that's
that well so we just our announcement
tweet we thought that were going to be
it and then we saw that Apple was like
steing this counter playay and we didn't
really care at first and well I mean I
still think it's great but then there
was some people who took Apple at face
value and again thought we lied cuz
Apple statement said we made a false
statement and that I was very like I was
like we did not lie we absolutely did
not make a false statement well
anecdotally like my perspective on this
I saw I think I saw your like Mastadon
post about it but it was a link to 9 to5
MH Mac and when I opened it and then I I
experienced this across multiple news
articles
afterwards they clearly had only gotten
Apple's press release initially y so
almost everybody's article which it
sounds like probably except for Tech
Crunch and and The Verge almost
everybody's article was literally their
statement M and so I was super confused
because they all were saying things like
alt stor is claiming that Apple approved
this but they didn't but nobody had alt
stores quote at least not in the
original articles so it's easy to see
when you're reading it as just a reader
or even as those press junkets MH uh
seeing it and being
like yeah they claimed that we approved
in the App Store but we didn't in like
assuming that's what was claimed even
though obviously it wasn't and so that
was then we had to put out like our
first ever like official statement we're
cuz I was like we just need to get ahead
of this like cuz it's like it's what
we're doing is fine I stand by I stand
by the fact that we have porn on alt
store it's hidden like you got to add
the source but it's something that
should exist so that was also part we
should highlight that too it's not like
you download app store and there's a
porn app in your face it's just it's
possible it is possible how alt store
works is you add sources and only once
you add a source will you see all the
apps from that source so if you download
alt store you will have no idea there's
hot tub any at all in it and so that's
how our SCT try to make but yeah another
thing is we just wanted to own the fact
because we knew that like porn is always
it's no one talks about it and it's so
popular and I just was like I just
didn't want to it's a huge thing and I
don't hate I'm not against porn and so I
thought would be important for us just
stand behind it just to own like the
same thing with apple like if we're
going to put on our store I'm going to
I'm going to back it I'm going to put
our name on it once you make that
decision yeah and so that was like a
whole thing but again yeah so we want to
do a whole press thing and then Apple
sent out their thing so then we sent out
our official statement which we me and
Shane just like sat here like for hours
yesterday like writing like oh you had
it it was like an image right with the
text inside it looked like you know
official press second exactly it's like
so funny it was it's a keynote slide we
put our icon in the corner put the font
it looks official oh nice but it's kind
of we learned like
controversy is makes us popular or just
like yeah it blew up we alt store
downloads are higher hot tubs down like
hot tubs like the number one like number
two app oh yeah this is the Strand
effect to the nth degree right seeing it
how many people would have any idea
about this if it wasn't for this
becoming a massive story yeah like alt
store I Che like Google trans it's like
at its peak searching alt store for ever
since hot tub came out and that's
included like the entire lifetime I'm
like apple really just like made it so
much bigger than it was and then people
it's a weird it's a weird strategic play
from their perspective right cuz on one
hand it normalizes it for way more
people to download an alternate store
which is not what they want but the flip
side
is they have some Assumption of what
kind of Leverage this gives them
politically right and like I don't
understand the European yeah world at
all in the states well to be honest I
don't understand it in the states either
but like it's certainly a divisive topic
that you could imagine them utilizing
but it's it's very uh ephemeral at least
to me my understanding of how the impact
is but certainly in the short term it
has to have just been massive for people
understanding that it was possible to
download third party stores that yes
that and the fact that we said it was
Apple approved raised a lot or made a
lot of conversations that people are
learning that Apple's involved in this
process cuz didn't know and now it's
front and center and so people having
that discussion I'm like this is good we
need people to know that Apple approves
and rejects apps from our store they
think this needs to be Pro so it had the
effect we did want in the end but yes I
app I just miscalculated how upset Apple
would be by that statement and I like
okay so sorry we're trying to be that
antagonistic I was just mad you blocked
mini vmac I'm getting back exactly yeah
this is really about Windows simulation
if y'all hadn't rejected it this we
wouldn't have done this and so it's like
I know it's kind of your
fault yeah man I just such an insane
story and hopefully people are getting
across what what I've felt every time
we've talked which is like you're just a
guy who likes technology and
likes games yeah and wants people to be
able to play them on their phones uh and
you sort of and a very talented
developer and strategically smart but
also kind person a weird Alchemy of of
things going on here I appreciate that
and
like I I I can't I don't know anybody
else who's gone through any sort of
Journey remotely like this uh and so
huge shout out to Shane for going
through this with you because who would
you reach out to
to understand what you're going through
it'd be zero people right like I can't
think of literally anybody exactly like
it's we are the two people in the world
that like are understanding this very
weird like mix of so many things going
on right now global politics and
Technical weird like uh Nuance it's it's
a weird combination of a lot of things
yeah like I saw a Business Insider news
article about like hot tub and it was
like how Apple a porn app and Trump's
tariffs are all connected I'm like oh
man now we're like in like us we're
getting involved in this yeah I will say
you want to be loud but there might be
there might be one area where you don't
want to get attention no yes very much
so oh man that's crazy well uh it's
funny like when I finally was like I'm
going to get the show back going and I
was like I have to start with Riley like
because I wanted to have you on for
forever uh I thought man this is perfect
timing cuz everything's really settled
down into something
right yeah I thought the next shoe to
drop was going to be uh who knows what's
going on with with the doj uh thing in
the US yeah um but they're certainly the
EU has created a potential playbook for
everybody else um and I guess you're
along for the ride uh for all of those
yeah we're just here to see like exactly
you said like our goal is just to make
all these apps just available like Delta
and well now those are in the App Store
but like there's just so many more apps
out there that hav exist so yeah it's
just we want to get those to be out
there and it's going to take time but
it's going to come to America eventually
we've been talking to the doj they know
us they it very surreal talking to them
because like we had like a zoom call
with them and they knew everything about
us and like I was like wow you know they
they were telling me my GBA fir history
they like oh you changed your paint on
your W no like wow y'all did your
research it's really cool like y'all
actually do know what you're talking
about here but I have gathered that like
I think most people's impression of
politicians uh or bureaucrats is like
government they don't understand how
anything Works which like obviously
there's truth to that and usually the
mouthpieces like the elected official
they aren't experts on it but the people
I know in US Senate and stuff like that
that are at the wonky policy level it's
always surprising like how deep they go
on these topics and I don't know if that
was your experience with the EU as well
but like yeah they e yeah it's always
surprising uh to me or it's a little uh
what's the right word it makes me feel a
little better about the world realizing
like there are nerds uh embedded through
all of this stuff you do actually
understand things better than I assume
that they do exactly yeah that's cool
well it'll be it'll be fun to watch you
uh this sounds dark it'll be fun to
watch you go through all of this but
like navigate all this is the right word
um hopefully it's less stressful than it
was at the beginning it's less stressful
but we just yeah we've learned to just
play everything as it comes we just like
yeah we have plans but we know things
come up and so most of it is just how
can we respond to whatever situation
arises which is fun like it keeps things
interesting for sure but yeah so and
patreon big shout out to them for
basically creating the mechanism for you
to the like ultimately The Leverage that
all these big players Apple epic if they
ever decide to expose or utilize it all
the leverage that they have is like
financial instruments essentially other
than legal exactly stuff and like you're
sort of outside of that to a degree
because you have a group of supporters
you're very small you aren't trying to
build a multi-billion Dollar business
with VC funding or anything and that
makes you agile in a way that's probably
very annoying uh for these big companies
that are used
to being able to apply
uh differently yes it is very annoying
for Apple I know that for a fact because
I I know that they cuz we can just
respond much faster than they can and
they'll take a long time decisions and
so that is our advantage for at least
them but in general yeah we can be skunk
work and do weird things or stuff a big
company can't do and I think that's so
important to who we are it's one of the
reasons we're not getting like FEC
funding or trying to blow up because I
think that would ruin what alt store and
or Al store and Delta is which is we are
Indie driven by us having our patreon it
means we're motivated to like make sure
our patreon's good and make sure that
we're treating our patrons well so
that's awesome all right well um I'll go
ahead and try to try to actually Land
This Plane then uh thank you for for the
extra time uh that you've given me from
our scheduled time oh it's been great
yeah so I want to end it the way that uh
I always in the show which is to ask you
uh what is a person or people out there
that have inspired you that you'd
recommend other check out C and yeah
good question so I have two if that's
fine like for yeah um the first one
probably most people listen to the show
will know the tap Bots crew like them
from the very beginning of when I was
work like starting to make apps I love
tweetbot and I was very inspired by the
fact they were at the time you two
person company just the developer and
designer doing everything and to me that
was like the biggest iPhone app like
everyone in the Apple Community like
talked about it and I was like wow if
two people can just like work on an app
and make a business together that's kind
of the dream and so that was directly
from them was a lot of inspiration for
just like doing me and Shane just us two
being independent and seeing what we can
do with it and so I just saw I think
yesterday they were they were giving
some hints that maybe they're
considering a blue sky client
which I know really love that I mean I
do love Maston for so much but the main
reason on Maston is because it has Ivory
like that's like I do love MTH on the
Val but man I it's like I'm such an app
snob I need the apps that work and
that's the reason I'm not on Blue Sky I
mean I am a blue sky but I don't use as
much it's because it's a native Blue Sky
app and it's not my favorite app it's
just I mean like I'll check it but like
Ivory is just nice and even threads at
least as an app I do appreciate like the
Finesse in it but whatever versus the
react native app of Blue Sky you mean
mhm yeah so so yeah so so the tapbots
crew I just am so inspired by them I
think they make great apps and always
wanted to someday make be successful as
a two-person company so I've achieved
that goal and so kind of owe that to
them and then the other is um a very
different but it's this Indie Creator
supper Mario broth it's
like broth a Blog that's focused on
Mario content and they like do deep
dives into very nerdy things about like
Nintendo games like they'll be like hey
in Mario Galaxy they have three
different Sprites they use for
Reflections and you don't see all of
them in the game but here they are or
they'll be like there's a like here's a
hidden room you can access that's not
intended to be accessed but like the
super nerdy nitty-gritty stuff from like
all Nintendo games I love that but why I
say they inspired is that was the first
patreon I ever donated to I just I
followed them on Twitter I love them
back when Twitter was good and I loved
them so much and I was like I want to
support them I just love this content
and I donate like $3 a month to them and
just like without really thinking about
it and it was the fact that I did that
that when Shane was talking about
patreon I was like oh yeah I I'm
supporting like supper Mario broth just
because they make such amazing content
for fun like I just wanted to support
them and so I was like you know what
maybe I could do that too like I could
just get like people who love my content
and support me and so really yeah oh
that's cool it was awesome and and I
love their content it's incredible they
do really detailed like dives into all
this stuff and I don't know the nerd in
me loves it so much and I love that they
spend so much time on it and yeah it's
like just a passion project yeah I think
that's the thing I think that's the
thing people appreciate about the the
Indie World generally too is just this
idea of like it
being doing stuff not because it makes
sense but because you're excited about
it y um that seeing people be excited
about a thing even if you don't care
about it on your own is in itself super
exciting mhm uh and so yeah that's cool
and patreon is such a good mechanism for
that kind of stuff it's it's it's
incredible like that's what I like just
shout out in general to patreon because
yeah like you said I would not be here
without today it is our entire source of
income and so many creators like allows
for so much creativity in the world and
art and yeah it's amazing and now
Apple's trying to take 30% of all of it
because of course like and just like a
man read The Room app things just like
ridiculous but yeah that was a weird
yeah I could go into long detail about
the weird Choice there where yeah they
tried to force them to switch over but
uh or I guess they did force them to
happening I'm like wow I can't believe
it apples God it's so bad yeah too much
of a tangent but ridiculous yeah but and
like to bring it back to sort of your
original thing though because like you
know we both have said many things about
our feelings on Apple policies over the
last few years But ultimately it's like
the the engineers there and the team the
designers there and the people building
things there are still building things
that we get really excited about
otherwise we wouldn't care in the first
place y um and it's it's the dichotomy
of the the people building things for
passion mixed with them doing things
that tick us off uh you know on the
policy level and everything that I think
makes people feel as strong as they do
otherwise you would have just
release this on Android and about your
day right like but to me like well I
like iPhones I like all this like it's
and I mean it's also a little more fun
to try to figure all this out on on like
it would too easy on Android but it's
like you know what I had to be creative
and figure something out uh that's funny
all right well um I guess to wrap this
up uh where can people find you and all
of your work well you can find me across
all the social medias nowadays I'm Riley
testat on madon R test madono and R test
on threads or riley. soal on Blue Sky
because of that fancy domain oh yes the
doain yes I love that yeah I do love
that yeah and for me too I haven't
decided yet if I'm going to continue
using the ending or if I'm just going to
end it with me talking so I'm just going
to talk and we'll see if I cut this out
or not Excell but right now launched is
on well launched fm.com is where you'll
find everything that's the easy one uh
that is also the Blue Sky handle because
of the fancy domain thing um and then
pretty much everywhere else it's
launched FM I think it might be just
launched on Macedon uh but you can find
all of that on on the website and that's
the best way to let me know if you're
excited to have the show back uh you
know let me know on any of the social
media platforms so that I feel really
good about myself uh cuz that's what
this is that's what this is all about uh
Riley thank you so much for uh uh easing
me back into this with such a fun
conversation I had a blast thanks I'm
honored to be the first one that you had
back